Guide to the Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg records,1849-1963.
Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg records,1849-1963
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg records, 1849-1963.
6054
Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg (Mecklenburg, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Three volumes which include a quarterly conference meeting minutes of the Mecklenburg charge and the Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg (1849-1893); a church membership register (1863-1883) containing lists of baptisms, marriages, probationers, members in full and class members, with removals, deaths and dismission; and a "Comprehensive Church Record of th Methodist Episcopal Church" (1882-1963) with much information on early Mecklenburg, the McIntyre settlement, area churches, circuits and villages.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg originated about 1823 in a Methodist Episcopal class near the McIntyre Settlement on the Ulysses Circuit, Genesee Conference. A division of the Ulysses Circuit in 1843 prompted the annexation of the Mecklenburg charge to the Enfield Circuit in 1844. The charge included appointments at Mecklenburg (where the church was located), Little Flatts (or Cayutaville) and Allen's.
A subsequent division or reorganization placed the Mecklenburg charge on the Hector Circuit in 1846. In 1849, the Mecklenburg charge was organized into a station "by itself," with a full-time pastor. (For a more thorough history, see item 3 in this collection.)
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The records of the Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg comprise three items (volumes): item 1 is quarterly conference meeting minutes for the Mecklenburg charge and Methodist Episcopal Church (1849-1893); item 2 is a church membership register (1863-1883)1 containing lists of baptisms, marriages, probationers, members in full, and class members, with removals, deaths and dismissions; and item 3 is also a church register (1882-1963)2 with contents same as item 2, plus an "Historical Record" (covering years [1817]-1963, incomplete), including a wide variety of information; a list of pastoral and statistical records; and lists of official church members.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Methodist Episcopal Church of Mecklenburg (Mecklenburg, N.Y.); Genesee Conference.Ulysses Circuit (N.Y.)
Subjects:
Church records and registers--New York (State)--Mecklenburg.; Methodist Episcopal Church--New York (State)--Mecklenburg.
Places:
Mecklenburg (N.Y.)--History.; Mecklenburg (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Schuyler County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.; Baptismal certificates.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Quarterly meeting minute book. October 29, 1849-August 19, 1893., Item 1
  The minutes record members present, officials present, appointments and elections, complaints, appeals, disciplinary cases, official and committee reports, resolutions, quarterly finances, preachers' salaries, and official meetings. Also appearing in the volume are three subscription lists (1883, 1873 and no date), for a new church and to clear a debt of $3100.
- Church register of Baptisms and Marriages, 1863-1883., Item 2
  Contains lists of baptisms (1863-1880) with names, dates, minister and remarks; marriages (1862-1883) including dates, names, minister, place of marriage and fee; probationers (1863-1882) listing dates, names, ages, residence, class leaders and remarks; members in full (alphabetical, no dates) listing names, deaths, removals and dismissions; alphabetical list of members (1867-1882), with information as in preceding list; and a record of the classes severally (no dates) including number, names, place of meeting, deaths, removals and dismissions.
- "Comprehensive Church Record of the Methodist Episcopal Church," 1882-1963., Item 3
  This volume contains a detailed history written October 23, 1885 covering the origins of Methodism in Mecklenburg and Mclntre Settlement (the "Old Ulysses Circuit"), with lists of preachers on the circuit and pastors on the Mecklenburg charge, and data on members, towns, other circuits, and area churches.
  A second history, citing revivals in the Mecklenburg Methodist Episcopal Church in 18[88] and 1889, and brief entries made by subsequent pastors in 1914-1924, 1933, and 1963, follow. After the histories are seven sections of membership information under the following headings:
  - "Pastoral and Statistical Record" (1882-1962)
    includes pastor's name, when appointed, estimated salary, salary received, probationers, deaths, local preachers, baptisms, church and real property values, benevolent contributions, and Sunday school statistics.
  - "Church Record of Official Members" (1882-1901)
    lists names of trustees, stewards, class leaders, and Sunday school superintendants, and when they served.
  - "Class Records" (few dates)
    lists class number, leaders and members, members' state in life and remarks (deaths, removals, dismissions, etc.)
  - "Probationers' Record" (1884-1905)
    lists names, state in life, when and by whom received, class number, date baptized, residence, and how disposed of.
  - "Members in Full Connection" (1884-1905)
    lists names, state in life, when and by whom received, class number and remarks (deaths, dismissions, removals).
  - "Marriage Record" (1882-1905)
    lists dates, names of parties, residence, places of birth, occupations of males, ages, officiating minister, and remarks.
  - "Record of Baptisms" (1883-1905)
    lists date, names, adult or infant, date of birth, parents' names, mode and place of baptism, officiating minister and remarks.